I think you are all probably thinking the same thing. You have a burning question. I felt like...
我想你们大概都在想同样的事情。 你有一个迫切的问题。我觉得...
I wouldn't be able to do the rest of my speaking tour without addressing this burning question.
如果不解决这个棘手的问题 我无法完成剩下的演讲
I was bombarded on Twitter today with the same question: "Have you tasted haggis?" [Laughter]
今天我在推特上被同样的问题轰炸了： “你尝过哈吉斯(羊肚，苏格兰的小吃)了吗？” [笑声]
The answer is, "No, I'm too scared."
答案是，“不，我太害怕了。”
I made the mistake of reading about how it is made before tasting it.
我犯了一个错误： 在品尝它之前，我先去查了下它是怎么做的
I've been told that you should do it the other way around, because then it is a lot less scary.
有人告诉我，其实是用另一种方法做的， 它不那么可怕
I'm trying to build up the courage. I have been told that the best way to [eat] this is in a burger.
我试着鼓起勇气 有人告诉我最好的吃法是夹在汉堡里吃
I don't know if that is actually true. No? Okay. There is a big disagreement in the room.
我不知道这是否真的如此。不是这样？好的。房间里有很大的分歧
On the count of three, all those in favor of haggis burger, [raise your hand]. Nobody? Okay. Haggis for breakfast?
我数到三，所有赞成哈吉汉堡的人请[举手]。没有人？好的。哈吉斯做早餐怎么样？
[AUDIENCE] Yeah! [ANDREAS] Ah, okay. Are there other formulations I should try?
[听众]不错！ [安德烈斯]啊，好的。 我应该尝试其他配方吗？
[AUDIENCE] Haggis on toast! [ANDREAS] Haggis on toast, very good...
[听众]哈吉斯吐司！ [安德烈斯]哈吉斯吐司，非常好......
[AUDIENCE] Intravenous. [Laughter]
[听众]静脉注射。 [笑声]
[ANDREAS] How about a corporate-sponsored haggis that is pretending to be an open haggis?
[安德烈斯]企业赞助的哈吉斯怎么样？
[Laughter] And was launched this morning? Okay. Let's talk about the elephant in the room: Libra.
[笑声]今天早上发布了？好吧 我们来谈谈房间里的大象：Libra
This morning, you probably heard that Facebook announced their "cryptocurrency," Libra.
今天早上，你可能听说过 Facebook宣布了他们的“加密货币”Libra
Whenever the price of bitcoin goes down, I receive calls from friends and family,
每当比特币价格下跌时， 我就会接到朋友和家人的电话，
asking if I am okay. "Are you okay? Is everything okay?" This time, I actually got a call from a friend's mother.
问我是否还好。 “你还好吗？一切都好吗？” 这一次，我实际上接到了朋友的母亲的电话
She asked me if I'm okay and the price has not even dropped!
她问我是否还好 这次价格甚至还没有下降！
Just the fact that Facebook launched a cryptocurrency led to the "Are you okay? Are you holding up?" question.
事实上，Facebook推出了加密货币 导致“你还好吗？你还在坚持吗？” 这种问题
"Do we need to airlift you out of Europe?" I am okay.
“我们需要把你从欧洲空运出去吗？”我还好。
I talked about this two or three years ago, that one day we would see this happen.
我在两三年前谈过， 有一天我们会看到这种情况发生
Today is the day, right? It is now happening.
就在今天，对吗？它已经发生了
But what exactly happened? What can we talk about today?
但究竟发生了什么？ 我们今天能聊些什么？
This morning, Facebook released a white paper. Not a cryptocurrency. Not a network. Not a project.
今天早上，Facebook发布了一份白皮书。 不是一个加密货币。不是一个网络。不是一个项目
Not even an application.
甚至不是一个应用程序
Just a white paper. Everybody is freaking out because they wrote a whitepaper. But there is a long road...
只是一张白皮书。每个人都吓坏了，因为 他们写了一份白皮书。但是，还有一条漫长的道路要走......
to go between the white paper and a production network available to two billion users, wrapped in...
在白皮书和完成一个可供20亿用户使用的网络之前，这个网络程序需要带着......
a candy-colored Farmville interface.
糖果色的Farmville界面
But when they released the white paper, people became really excited. How many of you read the white paper?
但当他们发布白皮书时，人们就变得非常兴奋。你们有多少人读过白皮书？
Excellent, quite a few. I'll be honest with you, I did a brief skim. It has been a busy day.
很棒，不少人。说实话，我只是简略浏览了一下。这是忙碌的一天
I received a bunch of calls from journalists who wanted to talk about it. I am not ready to talk about it.
我收到了许多记者打来的电话 他们想聊聊这件事。我还没准备好谈论它
This will take a lot more study. I will not talk too much about the technology today.
这将需要更多的研究。 我不会在今天过多的谈论技术
We don't really know how this will play out. I want to talk about what has changed.
我们真的不知道结果会怎样 我想谈谈发生了什么变化
Everything changed this morning. This is something we have been predicting for more than three years.
今天早上一切都改变了。 这是我们已经预测了三年多的事情
It changes everything, whether or not Facebook is able to get Libra into production.
无论Facebook是否能够让天秤座投入到生产环境中，它都改变了一切，
The mere fact that this whitepaper was dropped has now set the bar. They dropped the gauntlet.
仅仅是这篇白皮书被删除的事实, 就已经设定了标杆。他们放弃了挑战
Silicon Valley is coming for banking in a big way. We predicted that this would happen.
硅谷正在大举进军银行业。 我们预测会发生这种情况
A lot of people thought it would be Amazon first. But turns out, it is Facebook - which is much worse...
很多人认为亚马逊会是第一个 但事实证明，是Facebook  - 这更糟糕......
than anyone had imagined possible. [Laughter]
比任何人想象的都可能更糟糕。 [笑声]
All right, about the whitepaper. If you haven't looked, this is a collaboration [between about] thirty [companies].
好的，关于白皮书。如果你还没有看过，这个是一个[约三十个公司]之间的合作
I have a feeling that within Facebook- Some people are saying this is the result of a year's effort.
我有一种感觉，在Facebook内部，-有些人 会说这是一年努力的结果
I have a feeling that they created this incubator / sandbox innovation lab, gathered thirty to forty...
我有一种感觉，他们创造了这个孵化器沙箱创新实验室， 聚集了三十到四十名...
bright people, locked them in a room, and slid pizzas under the door until the whitepaper came out.
聪明的人，将他们锁在房间里，然后从门底下滑进披萨饼，直到白皮书出来
The whitepaper is actually very impressive, in terms of the technology vision. These people are very serious.
就技术前景而言，白皮书实际上非常令人印象深刻。这些人非常认真
[They seem] well-informed about what we are doing in the cryptocurrency and blockchain space.
[他们似乎]对我们在加密货币和区块链领域正在做的事情了如指掌
They cherry-picked some features of the best cryptocurrencies, the state-of-the-art technology,
他们挑选了一些最好的加密货币的功能，最先进的技术，
and then they [plan to] advance it a bit.
然后他们[计划]改进一下
They synthesized it into something that [sounds] quite impressive from a technology perspective.
他们将它合成为某种从技术角度来看令人印象深刻的东西
It has taken ideas from Ethereum, like a virtual machine for execution of smart contracts and gas.
他借鉴了以太坊的理论， 比如用于执行智能合约和Gas的虚拟机
A Merkle state tree that can be added to Merkle Mountain Ranges, or the Ethereum state tree.
可以添加到默克尔树的Merkle状态树， 或Ethereum状态树
An embedded or intrinsic digital currency. A proof-of-authority, federated network of validators,
一种嵌入式的数字货币。 Proof-of-aythority算法，验证者联合网络,
similar to Ripple or EOS, things that are kind of blockchains but not quite.
类似于Ripple或EOS，这是一种区块链，但不完全
Their consensus algorithm is not exactly new. It is a Byzantine fault tolerant consensus algorithm,
他们的共识算法并不新鲜。 它是拜占庭容错一致性算法，
which is not proof of work, but they say they want to move it to proof-of-stake.
他们说，这不是工作量证明 他们想把它转移到股权证明
Some very interesting stuff there. They mashed [these components] together...
有一些很有趣的东西。 他们将[这些组件]混合在一起......
and created something that is impressive from a technology perspective.
并创造了令人印象深刻的东西 -- 从技术角度来看
It is impressive because of who did it, not based on what was actually done.
这令人印象深刻， 不是因为实际做了什么，而是因为谁在做
If I had released that whitepaper with thirty collaborators, everybody would have [shrugged it off].
如果我作为三方合作者发布了那份三十页的白皮书，每个人都会[耸耸肩]
"Okay, there's another blockchain..."
“好的，又出来另一个区块链......”
But when a company with two billion users does that, people understand that this could have a big impact.
但是当拥有20亿用户的公司这么做时， 人们明白这可能会产生很大的影响
Now we will see whether this [idea] survives its first contact with Facebook's corporate [managers].
现在我们将看到这个[想法]是否在Facebook的公司[经理]的首次披露后中存活下来
At the moment, this is an incubated project. It is idealistic. It is [rather] aggressive in its vision.
目前，这是一个正在孵化的项目。 这是理想主义的。它的愿景相当激进
It is focused on being decentralized, a bit now and even more in the future.
它侧重于分散化， 现在有一点，将来会更多
Permissioned now, permissionless in the future. Proof-of-authority now, proof-of-stake in the future.
现在采用准入制，将来无限制 现在采用权威证明，未来采用股权证明
A very progressive, aggressive vision.
一个非常进步，积极的愿景
But that vision will run straight into a bunch of MBAs and lawyers at Facebook headquarters.
但是，这个愿景将直接影响到一堆 Facebook总部的MBA和律师
"Whoa there!" [Laughter] Or maybe not. Let's see.
“哇，看那个！” [笑声] 或者可能不会。让我们来看看
It will be really interesting to see how much of this vision survives into deployment.
这是非常有趣的 看看这种愿景有多少在部署中能得到延续
That will determine what happens next. If it survives into deployment, it could become very successful...
这将决定接下来会发生什么。如果他在部署中存活下来，它可能会变得非常成功......
and a huge moneymaker.
而且是一个巨大的赚钱机器
The MBAs will become very excited.
MBA将变得非常兴奋
Some things in the white paper are quite surprising. For example, the use of an association to segregate it...
白皮书中的一些内容非常令人惊讶。 例如，使用三方合作模式来把它和Facebook隔离开来......
from Facebook, and a promise to not use the profile information on your Facebook account.
并承诺不使用您的Facebook帐户上的个人资料信息
Do you have a Facebook account? I sure as hell don't.
你有一个Facebook帐户？我才不呢
[Will they] use that in collaboration with the currency? That would be a no-no, right?
[他们会]与法币合作使用它吗？ 那是不被许可的，对吧？
At the moment, it says that information will not be shared and used for surveillance.
目前，它的说法是信息不会被分享并用于监视
It will not be used for any of these- Oh, one second. Sorry. "We are sending you this very important email...
它不会用于任何这些 - 哦，等一下。 抱歉。 “我们给你发了一封非常重要的邮件......
to notify you about changes to our Terms & Conditions. Please reading the following 600 pages of gibberish...
通知您有关我们的条款和条件的更改 请阅读以下600页的胡言乱语...
to understand how we completely removed due-process and your privacy. Thank you very much!"
了解我们如何完全删除您的正当程序和您的隐私。非常感谢你！”
"The Facebook Team." [Laughter]
“来自于Facebook团队。” [笑声]
So that email just came to me from the future. It was written by an MBA.
所以这封电子邮件是我从未来收到的， 它是由一位MBA编写的
It will change all of those promises the moment this becomes successful.
一旦它取得成功， 它将改变所有这些承诺
If you think that I'm kidding, look at what happened to Whatsapp.
如果你认为我在开玩笑， 就看看Whatsapp发生了什么
The founders of that company started with the same kind of idealistic vision,
该公司的创始人一开始也具有同样的理想主义愿景，
and left, forgoing hundreds of millions of dollars in pay and bonuses. "Use Signal."
他离开Fackbook，放弃了数以亿计美元的薪水和奖金。 “并发出信号。”
"Do not use Whatsapp if you are a dissident, an activist, or a political operative."
“如果你是持不同政见者，一个活动家，或一个政治人物，请不要使用Whatsapp，"
"If your communication's confidentiality will make the difference between surviving or not,
“如果您的通信保密攸关生死的话
if you are one of the millions of people who is marching in Hong Kong this week, don't use Whatsapp."
如果你是本周在进行数百万人游行的人之一，不要使用Whatsapp。“
Will something similar happen? I'm a bit of a cynic. I think that large corporations have a tendency to...
类似的事情会发生吗？我有点愤世嫉俗。 我认为大公司倾向于......
swallow innovation, rip out the disruptive [parts], and spit out something neutered.
吞下创新，摧毁颠覆性，然后吐出一些绝育的东西
Something that is profit-making while exploiting users, because that is their obligation to their shareholders.
在剥削用户的同时盈利， 这是他们对股东的义务
But we will see. Maybe it won't be so.
但我们会看到。也许不会是这样
That is what happened on the technical front this morning.
这就是今天早上发生的技术方面的事情
Now, everybody is trying to solve what I call the three-body problem.
现在，每个人都在努力解决的这个问题，我称之为三体问题
Until now, we were looking at this space as the interaction between two major forces:
到现在为止，我们一直把这个领域看作 两大力量之间的相互作用：
on one side, we have nation-state fiat money, as we derisively call it in the crypto space;
一方面，我们有民族国家的法定货币， 正如我们在加密空间中嘲弄它一样;
on the other side, we have the people's money, open and borderless cryptocurrency for everyone to use.
另一方面，我们有人民的货币--开放 和无边界加密货币供所有人使用
These two forces are orbiting and exerting pressure on each other.
这两股力量在轨道上运行 并互相施加压力
Right now, cryptocurrencies are a [bunch of] tiny little asteroids.
现在，加密货币只是 一批微小的小行星
Fiat is a big planet full of very successful life forms, who are looking up at the sky and wondering,
打个比方，法币世界是一个充满非常成功的生命形式的大星球，他们仰望星空，想搞明白
"What is that shiny thing? It seems to be getting bigger." You know, the experience of the dinosaurs.
“那闪亮的东西是什么？它看起来越来越大了。”  你知道，那就是恐龙的经历
[Some say], "Don't worry, it's pretty. Look at how nice the sunset looks!"
[有人说]，“别担心，它很漂亮。 夕阳多么美好啊！“
"Oh, it keeps getting bigger..."
“哦，它一直在变大......”
Solving the two-body problem from a political perspective, trying to figure out what happens...
从政治角度解决两体问题，试图弄清楚这种情况下会发生什么......
when nation-states and open cryptocurrencies collide, is difficult enough.
当民族国家和开放的加密货币发生碰撞时会发生什么，这是很难的
We can't tell, because nations are positioning themselves in different ways.
我们无法分辨，因为各国的法律政策不同
Some are freaked out and ban it outright. China has banned it about 1,726 times so far.
有些人吓坏了，直接禁止它。 到目前为止，中国已经禁止它约1,726次
All ineffectively. India has banned it, kind of, twice.
这一切都无效。印度已经禁止了它两次
Ecuador was one of the first to ban it completely. Yet in many advanced nations, cryptocurrencies...
厄瓜多尔是最先完全禁止它的国家之一。 然而在许多发达国家，加密货币......
have actually been thriving.
实际上一直在蓬勃发展
In what we call "free societies," the idea of banning private currency is constitutionally problematic.
在我们所说的“自由社会”中，禁止的想法 私人货币在宪法上存在问题。
Both the United States' Constitution and the United Kingdom's constitution protect freedom-
美国的宪法和 英国的宪法保护自由 -
Oh, wait. You don't have [a constitution]. Anyway... [Laughter]
等一下。其实你没有[宪法]...... [笑声]
The Magna Carta, let's say, protects freedom of speech. Money is a form of political speech.
我们说，宪章保护言论自由。 而金钱是政治言论的一种形式
That is something cherished in free societies. It is not so easy to just ban [cryptocurrencies].
这是自由社会所珍视的东西。 仅仅禁止[加密货币]并不容易
But there was a lot of tension this morning, with a big discussion on Twitter that I reluctantly got involved in.
但今天早上气氛很紧张 我不情愿地参与Twitter上的一场讨论
It was about whether Facebook's Libra is a cryptocurrency or not. Let's take a quick poll.
这是关于Facebook的天秤座是否是一个 加密货币。让我们快速来个投票
All those who say that it is a cryptocurrency, [raise your hand]. All those who say it is not, [raise your hand].
所有那些说它是加密货币的人，[举起你的手]。所有那些说不是的人，[请举手]
All those who haven't decided yet, [raise your hand]. That is okay. I don't think that question makes sense.
所有还没有决定的人，[举手]。 好的，可以。我认为这个问题没有意义
It doesn't make sense because Facebook's Libra is new. It is a corporate digital currency.
这不合理，因为Facebook的Libra是新的。它是一种企业数字货币
We haven't seen corporate currencies since the opium wars, medieval feudalism, and the Medici.
自从鸦片战争，中世纪封建主义和美第奇以来, 我们还没有看到公司货币
How fitting that with the dawn of corporate neo- feudalism, one of the leading corporate states,
这与新封建主义的兴起是多么的契合， 一个主要的大公司组织
the supra-nation of Facebook, is launching its own currency.
名为Facebook的超级国家，正在推出自己的货币
Things will become very interesting, for a number of reasons. We now have a three-point stand-off.
事情会变得非常有趣，原因有很多。 我们现在陷入了一个三角僵局
It is now money of the corporations, money of the people, and the money of government.
它现在是公司的货币，人民的货币和政府的货币
All three will exist. None of them are going away soon. In fact, more will join. The doors have been opened.
这三个都会存在。他们都不会很快消失。 事实上，会有更多的公司加入。门已经打开了
Facebook is the first of the FANGs; the rest are baring their fangs and ready to go.
Facebook是'FANGs'中的第一个; 其余人都露出了獠牙，准备出发了
"FANGs," if you don't know, [stands for] Facebook-Amazon-Netflix-Google...
“FANGs”，[代表] Facebook- Amazon - Netflix -Google...
and the billion-dollar tech companies of Silicon Valley. There is also Twitter, Uber, and Airbnb.
以及硅谷十亿美元的科技公司。 还有Twitter，Uber和Airbnb
The era of internet currencies just opened.
互联网货币时代刚刚开启
Silicon Valley is coming for the banks, in a way that has never happened before.
硅谷正在向银行业进军 以前从未发生过的方式
The bankers have been very comfortable until now.
到目前为止，银行家一直很舒服
I went to a conference in Zurich and spoke to banking executives in 2014. I told them,
我在2014年去了苏黎世的一个会议并发言，我告诉银行业高管
"Listen. Instead of hiring blockchain consultants to show you how to square a circle, undo the disruption,
“听着。不要雇用区块链顾问来教你如何解决问题
and pretend to do blockchain, you should hire a former executive from the music industry."
并假装采用区块链做了什么， 你应该雇用来自音乐界的前高管。“
"Ask them what it felt like when the internet came for their industry."
“问问他们，当互联网进入他们的行业的时候是什么感觉“
"When did you realize you couldn't do anything about it? How did you feel when you started losing to Apple?"
“你什么时候意识到你无能为力呢？ 当你开始输给Apple时，你什么感觉？“
Guess what? The banks had [more than] ten years to figure this shit out,
你猜怎么着？银行有超过十年的时间来弄清楚这个，
how they would handle digital currencies.
他们要如何处理数字货币
The music industry should have made a deal with Napster; instead, they fought with tooth and nail,
音乐界应该与Napster达成协议; 但他们的做法正好相反，他们用牙齿和钉子进行斗争，
and handed the entire industry to Apple.
并将整个行业交给了Apple
The banks should have made a deal with Bitcoin when it was the cuddly gecko of cryptocurrencies.
银行应该与比特币达成协议 特别是当比特币还是加密货币的可爱壁虎的时候
Facebook is a Triceratops [of social media] and it is coming for their industry, to disrupt a lot of things.
Facebook是社交媒体的三角龙， 他将颠覆许多行业
[It may sound] really weird, but the first to be affected by this will be retail banks.
[听起来可能]真的很奇怪， 但第一个受此影响的将是零售银行
Not the big bad investment banks who make shady deals to bail out dictators and stuff like that.
不是那些大型投资银行 他们做一些见不得人得交易来拯救独裁者之类的
The banks that actually serve customers.
而是真正为客户服务的银行
Most big investment banks stopped taking checking and savings customers [in consumer markets]...
大多数大型投资银行[在消费者市场]都不再接受支票和[储蓄客户]  ......
four or five years [ago].
这发生在四年或五年[前]
"You people don't pay enough. You're not worthy of banking."
“你们这些人付的钱不够， 你不值得银行为你服务“
But retail banks, the corner branch where you know the banker,
但零售银行，你认识银行家的那些街角支行，
or at least [you can call them] to discuss your overdraft ballooning again.
或者至少[你可以打电话给他们] 再次讨论下你的透支问题
Those retail banks actually serve customers, even the unbanked and underbanked,
那些零售银行实际上是为客户服务的 即使是没有银行存款和存款不足的人
gradually expanding their reach.
他们依靠这些业务逐渐扩大他们的影响力
They will be hit hard by this new phenomenon, because Facebook not only has two billion users,
但他们将受到这种新现象的重创， 因为Facebook不仅拥有20亿用户，
but they know all their preferences and behavior patterns.
他们还知道用户的所有偏好和行为模式
They can use that to drop the cost of banking and wrap it in a candy-colored user interface.
他们可以用它来降低银行业务的成本 并将其包装成糖果色的用户界面
Every time you make a purchase [with Libra], the application will tickle your dopamine receptors a bit.
每次你使用[Libra]交易时， 该应用程序让你分泌出更多的多巴胺
It will encourage you to do or not do certain things, play with you like a mouse in a psychology experiment,
它会鼓励你做或不做某些事情， 就像心理学实验里的老鼠
where you can't see [the edges of] the maze because the walls are too high.
你看不到迷宫的[边缘]，因为墙壁太高了
This will be very interesting as it plays out.
当这一切发生的时候，这将是非常有趣的
To those of us who have been paying attention to the rise of techno neo-feudalism, it is terrifying.
对于我们这些一直关注的人来说， 技术新封建主义的兴起，令人恐惧
Facebook will be effective at disrupting regulation in a way that banks have not been able to.
Facebook将有效的打破监管 以银行无法做到的方式
Facebook is now going after central banks.
Facebook正在瞄准各国央行
Yes, they have a basket of currencies to create some kind of stablecoin thing,
是的，他们锚定一篮子货币来创造某种稳定的东西，
but that stablecoin will be stable vis-à-vis your local currency that is hyperinflating.
但是，相对于稳定币， 您的本地货币正在恶性通货膨胀
I talked about that this morning. Imagine that you are the government in India or Argentina,
我今天早上讲过 设想你是印度或阿根廷的政府，
and you want to follow an inflation or devaluation policy, but 10% of your population has moved on to Libra.
而且你想实行通货膨胀或贬值政策， 但是你们10％的人口都转而采用Libra
They can put their savings in the "hard" currency of Facebook. Well, not really a hard currency.
他们可以把他们的储蓄用在Facebook发行的通货上。好吧，不是真正的硬通货
It doesn't really have a monetary policy, so they say, but it is harder than the Argentinian peso.
它没有真正的货币政策，但他们说， 但它比阿根廷比索更通用
It is harder than the Turkish lira, the Indian rupee, and more than a hundred currencies around the world.
它比土耳其里拉，印度卢比和全世界超过一百种货币都更通用
The central banks will lose one of the big levers of power they have over the economy.
央行将失去他们拥有的对经济的权力杠杆的一项重要权力
What will they do, ban Facebook? Shut down 10% of their economy? They will try.
他们会怎么做，禁止Facebook？ 关闭10％的经济？他们会尝试
They have been trying to ban Facebook during protests, coup d'états of dictatorships, and revolutions.
他们一直试图在抗议期间禁止Facebook， 通过独裁政变和革命
They will fail. They will try to regulate Facebook.
但他们会失败。 然后他们将试图规范监管Facebook
Imagine the poor regulators, paid almost nothing, in their tweed suits.
想象一下可怜的监管机构， 穿着斜纹软呢套装，几乎没什么薪水
Academics from the economics ministry, facing an army of Wall Street lawyers in their tiny country,
面对经济部的学者 一群华尔街律师在他们这个小小的国家，
filling the parking lot of the local airport with Gulfstream [aircraft] in a row,
当地机场被湾流[飞机]排的满满的
"Let's talk about what we will do to your economy."
“让我们来谈谈我们能对您的经济做些什么”
If you didn't realize it, Facebook is planning [to launch] consumer and retail level SDRs.
如果你没有意识到，Facebook正在计划 [推出]消费者和零售层面的SDR(特别提款权)
Who knows what an SDR is? A few people.
谁知道SDR是什么？只有几个人知道
The International Monetary Fund is a global institution that is not [officially] controlled by governments.
国际货币基金组织是一个不受政府[官方]控制的全球性机构
It uses contributions from member states,
它使用成员国的捐款
a basket of currencies, to issue a pseudo- currency called Special Drawing Rights.
锚定一篮子货币，发出的货币称为特别提款权
[SDRs] are part of the international framework of free-floating exchange rates.
[特别提款权]是自由浮动汇率国际框架的一部分
They are the lender of last resort for governments. They do so in a very predatory manner.
他们是政府的最后贷款人。 他们以一种非常掠夺的方式运行
They impose extreme austerity on the governments which fall into their clutches, asset-strip their industries,
他们对落入他们掌控的政府实施极端的紧缩政策，剥离他们的产业
their water plants, railroads, and telecommunications companies.
他们的水厂，铁路和电信公司
Well, guess what? Facebook wil do that now.
好吧，猜猜怎么着？ Facebook现在就会这样做
If you think about what Libra is, it is a special drawing rights pseudo-currency, based on a basket of currencies,
如果你想一想Libra是什么，这是一个基于一篮子货币的特别提款权伪货币
that is funded by consumer activity, in the same countries where the government will ask them...
这是由消费者活动资助的 在以往，这些资助者的国家政府会限制......
for a loan or try to curtail their activity.
贷款或试图减少他们的活动
This is very serious stuff. We just went post-national.
这是非常严肃的事情。 我们刚刚进入后国家阶段
The power to control money used to be the exclusive prerogative of states.
控制货币的权力曾经是国家的专属特权
That has been kicked in the nuts by Bitcoin and [threatened with] decapitation by Libra this morning.
这已经被比特币和[今天早上]的Libra斩首
Central bank control over monetary policy ended this morning. Technology companies...
央行对货币政策的控制在今天早上结束了。科技公司......
currently worth a trillion dollars [total] are taking the ability to mint their own money.
目前市值1万亿美元[总计] 有能力铸造自己的钱
They will radically transform their business models, generating more money than you can ever imagine.
他们将从根本上改变他们的商业模式， 赚的钱比你想象的多
Very soon, they will dwarf the GDP of at least one third of the nations on this planet.
很快，它们至少会使这个星球上三分之一的国家的GDP相形见绌
When the IMF comes calling, most governments cower in fear.
当国际货币基金组织来电话时， 大多数政府都在恐惧中畏缩
But they have no idea how much worse it will be when Facebook, Google, or Apple comes calling.
但他们不知道当Facebook，谷歌或苹果公司来电时，情况会有多糟糕
Maybe even Twitter can take down a few governments. It is big enough. Why not? Soon, Uber will be dictating...
也许Twitter甚至可以推翻一些政府。 它够大了。为什么不？不久，优步将发号施令......
not just to taxi drivers, but to the local council and maybe even the cabinet of ministers.
不只是对出租车司机，而是对地方议会 甚至可能是对部长内阁
We [are approaching] a new world in which three forces will be competing: money of the people,
我们[正在接近]一个新的世界，其中三股力量将参与竞争：人民的货币
money of the state, and money of the corporations.
国家的货币和公司的货币
That is a crossroads. We need to make some very careful choices. I am hopeful for a number of reasons.
那是一个十字路口。我们需要做一些非常谨慎的选择。我满怀希望，是因为以下几个原因：
They will actually make a contribution to the technology, whether they want to or not.
无论他们是否愿意，他们实际上会为这项技术做出贡献，
They will introduce one billion people to the wrong kind of cryptocurrency,
他们将为10亿人口引入错误的加密货币
just like AOL introduced people to the wrong kind of internet. [Applause] Here is where it becomes tricky.
就像AOL把人们引入了错误的互联网。 [掌声]这就是问题变得棘手的地方
At this point, we need to decide how to differentiate [based on] our principles.
在这一点上，我们需要决定如何[基于]我们的原则进行区分
I have talked about the fundamental principles I care about in blockchains.
我已经谈过了根本问题 我所关心的区块链的原则
Sometimes I call them the five pillars of open blockchains, or the eight criteria. I lose count.
有时我称他们为开放区块链的五大支柱，或八个标准。我没有认真计数
It is somewhere between five and eight, but you should always [scrutinize] a system that is trying to take over...
它介于5到8之间，但你应该这样做 仔细[审查]一个试图接管的系统......
the foundational technology of money in your world.
在你的世界里，试图接管货币的基本技术
Is it open? What does "open" mean? Is it open for anyone to access and participate without vetting?
它是开放的吗？ “开放”是什么意思？开放意味着：任何人都可以访问和参与而无需审查吗？
Can anyone send a transaction without providing identification?
任何人都可以发送交易，不用提供身份的证明吗？
Is it? We don't know yet. We will see. The white paper [claims] it is [open].
是这样的吗？我们还不知道。我们会在将来看到。 白皮书[声称]它是[开放]的
We [will need to wait and see for] what the currency actually does.
我们[将拭目以待] 这个货币实际上怎么做
Is it borderless? I can tell you right now, it will not be borderless.
它是无国界的吗？我现在可以告诉你， 它不会是无国界的
There is only one borderless, global cryptocurrency of any value and meaning today. That is bitcoin.
今天，只有一个无国界的全球性的有价值和意义的加密货币，唯有比特币
It is maybe as good as the U.S. dollar at being borderless. But Facebook will not be in China.
在无国界这一点上，它或许和美元一样好，但Facebook不会进入中国
I can guarantee you that Libra will not launch in China. They will have their own, launched by WeChat.
我可以保证Libra不会在中国流通 他们将拥有自己的数字货币，由微信推出
Or a subsidiary wholly owned by the People's Republic of China, the central politburo.
或者由中国人民银行全资拥有的子公司推出
Like Facebook is a subsidiary of the NSA... [Laughter]
就像Facebook是美国国家安全局的子公司...... [笑声]
It will not launch in Russia either.
它也不会在俄罗斯推出
Are they going to give up their monetary sovereignty to a dude from Silicon Valley?
他们会放弃他们的货币吗？ 把货币主权交给硅谷的一个家伙？
It will not launch in a bunch of other places with unbanked people who actually need this.
它不会在其他地方发布 而没有银行账户的人其实需要这个
It will not be borderless. In fact, quite the opposite.
它不会是无国界的。事实上，恰恰相反
We have entered the era of Cold War-esque currency wars.
我们已进入了冷战式的货币战争时代
An Iron Curtain for currencies will drop, like we have never seen before.
货币的铁幕将下降， 我们以前从未见过这种情况
We will see a split between East and West in the evolution of state-based and corporate currencies.
我们将看到在国家和公司货币的演变中，东西方之间的分裂
Of the three, only open cryptocurrencies will go everywhere [around the world].
三种力量中，只有开放的加密货币将遍布世界各地
[Libra] will probably not be neutral.
[Libra]不可能会保持中立
Neutrality requires that the protocol allow transactions from anyone to anyone, [anywhere], for any purpose.
中立性要求协议必须能做到: 任何人之间，在[任何地方]，出于任何目的都可以进行交易
A lot of open cryptocurrencies do that. I very much doubt that Libra will do that.
许多开放的加密货币都是这样做的。 但我非常怀疑Libra会这样做
The moment they [allow] that, the subpoenas will start flying.
如果他们[允许]那样做，那一刻他们就会收到传票
The most important [detail for] a subpoena is knowing where to serve it, right? That will be easy.
传票中最重要的[细节]是知道在哪里开展了服务？这很容易
They have an office which accepts service of process, so that is where [governments] will send the subpoenas.
他们有一个接受流程服务的办公室，这就是[政府]发出传票的地方
Where do you send the Bitcoin subpoenas? Aha! Can you send them to 127.0.0.1 (localhost IP address)?
你要发给比特币传票？啊哈！ 你能发送到127.0.0.1（localhost IP地址）吗？
[Laughter] [Applause] We will process them immediately.
[笑声] [掌声] 我们会立即处理这些问题
So it will not be neutral. It will not be censorship resistant.
所以它不会是中立的。它不能抵制审查制度
Large corporations like that, bound by jurisdictional regulations, are obliged to censor transactions.
像这样的大公司，受司法管辖法规的约束，有义务审查交易
[As an American], you cannot send a transaction to an Iranian, a Venezuelan, or a North Korean.
[作为一个美国人]，您无法发送交易 给伊朗人，委内瑞拉人或朝鲜人
You cannot receive [money] from a Russian or Chinese citizen without properly vetting who they are,
如果没有适当的审查, 你不能从俄罗斯人或中国人那里收到[钱]
who their parents are, when they were born, where they live, and which companies they own.
政府需要审查收款人父母是谁，他们的出生日期， 他们住在哪里，他们拥有哪些公司
This happens every time you try to send a wire transfer.
每次尝试发送电汇时都会发生这种情况
[Libra] will not be immutable. They say in the white paper that [it will be] immutable,
[Libra]不会一成不变。他们说那将是[不可变的]白皮书
but the moment you make a transaction funding some abhorrent and inexcusable activity,
但当你为一些令人憎恶和不可原谅的活动提供资金时
subpoenas will start flying and the "immutable" network will be muted pretty damn fast.
传票将开始飞来飞去， “不可变”的网络将很快被静音
That is pretty easy to do when you have a consortium of validators and no cost for modifying the history.
以前你可以无需任何费用就可以轻易篡改交易记录，当你有一个财团时，这很容易做到
Proof-of-work makes it [practically] impossible, even if 100% of the miners collude and try to change history,
但如果采用工作量证明的机制， 那么即使100％的矿工串通并试图改变历史，
without expending the same amount of energy.
如果没有消耗相同的能量，那也是不可能的
This means with every day that passes, the energy cost increases. Within a day or two, it is an undue burden.
这意味着每天通过增加能源成本 。在一两天内，这是一个过度的负担
It is almost impossible, even if you could find and coerce all of the miners. They wouldn't be able to do it.
即使你能找到并强迫所有的矿工。他们也无法做到篡改历史
It is not "won't," it is "can't." Can't is much better than won't.
它不是“不愿意”，而是“不能”。不能比不愿意好得多
[But Libra] will not be immutable. It might be auditable and transparent. We don't know yet.
[但Libra]不会一成不变。它可能 是可审计和透明的。我们还不知道详细情况
If it is audible and transparent, it will not be private.
如果它是可审计和透明的，它将不是私密的
We are probably only a few years from a giant freaking leak, where all of your financial data 'are belong to us.'
我们可能隔几年就会发生一次巨大的惊人泄密，您的所有财务数据都"属于我们"
Again. [Laughter]
历史再次重复。 [笑声]
If it is stored in the blockchain in a transparent manner and you don't have any privacy controls --
如果它以透明的方式存储在区块链中，你没有任何隐私控制 -
you know, the kind that "criminals" use, but at least they are smart about privacy --
你知道，这可以区分“罪犯”， 但至少他们对隐私很聪明 -
all of that information will be leaked.
所有这些信息都将被泄露
All of your purchases will now be visible to friends and family.
现在你所有的交易行为都将让朋友和家人看到
[Each of us] probably has a very good friend we've made a pact with: "If I get hit by a bus,
[我们每个人]可能都有一个非常好的朋友 我们签订了协议：“如果我被公共汽车撞了，
I need you to take my laptop, erase my browsing history, and shred all of my bank statements... [Laughter]
我需要你拿我的笔记本电脑，擦掉我的浏览历史，并且粉碎我所有的银行对账单...... [笑声]
before my mom gets to the house. [Do we understand each other]?"
在我妈妈到家之前。 [我们彼此承诺]“
Financial privacy is a human right. Society doesn't work as a panopticon.
财务隐私是一项人权。 社会并不像一个圆形监狱
We have secrets because we're social animals. That gives us the freedom to express our freaky nature.
我们有秘密，因为我们是社交动物。 这给了我们表达自己的怪异本性的自由
We all differ a bit from the expectations and conformity of society. At least, I hope we do.
我们与社会的整合的预期有所不同 。至少，我希望我们这样做
Because if we don't, what kind of society is that? [Must we] absolutely conform to the expectations...
因为如果我们不这样做，那是什么样的社会？[我们必须]完全符合期望......
of your stuck-up neighbors?
符合你的高傲的邻居的期望？
Individuality, expression, freedom is privacy.
个性，表达，自就就是隐私
We don't want our financial records blasted to the world. But that will happen next [with Libra].
我们不希望我们的财务记录被曝光到全世界。但这将会发生[如果采用Libra的话]在下一步
It may be auditable and transparent, but not very private. This is not a blockchain I'm interested in.
它可能是可审计的透明的，但不是隐私的。这不是我感兴趣的区块链
More importantly, as I have said many times before, we are standing at a fork in the road.
更重要的是，正如我之前多次说过的那样，我们正站在一个岔路口
On the one hand, we have surveillance money. On the other, we have free, open, and private people's money.
一方面，我们有受监管的货币。 另一方面，我们有自由，开放和私人的货币
Guess what will happen with this new currency? The timetable to cashless societies has accelerated.
猜猜这种新货币会发生什么？ 无现金社会的进程已经加快
Cashless societies are nothing to celebrate. They [will be] without freedom or democracy.
无现金社会没什么值得庆祝的 他们[将]没有自由或民主
They are fragile, without the possibility of an exit plan or release valve. Where one election could be the last.
它们很脆弱，没有退出计划或释放阀门的可能性。每一次选举都可能是最后一次
You only need to get it wrong once. Just stay at home and say, "I don't care about politics."
你只需要弄错一次。只要呆在家里说，“我不关心政治。”
All of the kooky old people go out and vote for an orange man, Brexit, or some shit like that.
所有古怪的老人都出去为英国脱欧投票，或者诸如此类的事情
You ask, "What the hell happened?"
你会问，“到底发生了什么事？”
In a world where you don't have cash, it is much worse than that.
在一个没有现金的世界里， 情况更糟糕
The government, a corporation, or payment processor can decide that you have done something "bad,"
政府，公司或支付处理程序可以决定你做了什么“坏事”
and turn off your financial future.
并冻结你未来的财务能力
They could make sure that you can't even buy food, let alone pay for rent or [utilities].
他们可以让你甚至不能买食物，更不用说支付租金或[公用事业]
If you think this isn't happening, it is happening right now in Hong Kong.
如果你认为这不会发生， 那现在正在香港发生的事情就是个例子
It is happening in China with the Sesame credit score system.
中国的芝麻信用评分系统就是这样
If you think that is not coming to a country like yours, study up on European history, [like] 1918 through 1945.
如果你认为这样的事情不会发生在你的国家 那我们研究欧洲历史，[比如] 1918年至1945年
Fascinating shit. We thought the U.K. had learned that lesson.
迷人的狗屎。我们认为英国已经吸取了教训
From what I have been seeing lately, [nope]. They are trying to repeat all of [that]. Great.
但从我最近看到的情况来看，[没有]。 他们试图重复这一切。太好了
Sometimes you need to teach the lesson twice. What will we do in the crypto space?
有时您需要两次教授课程 我们将在加密空间做些什么？
We will start differentiating.
我们将开始区分
Over the next couple of years, expect a lot of crypto projects to focus on what their principles are.
在接下来的几年里，我们期待很多加密项目专注于他们的原则
Now, there is a lot of confusion. We are dealing with an 18-dimensional, partial differential equation...
现在，有很多困惑。我们正在处理一个18维偏微分方程......
of a three-body problem.
一个三角问题
Everything is pulling on everything else. Six degrees of freedom. It is very complicated.
所有的东西都在拉动其他的东西， 有六个自由度。这很复杂
Who knows will happen next? Look, Facebook went to India.
谁知道接下来会发生什么？ 瞧，Facebook去了印度
Uh, India wants to devalue [the rupee]. Indian people are going into cryptocurrency; others are being blocked.
呃，印度希望贬值[卢比]。 印度人开始使用加密货币;其他人则被封锁了
What happens next? Nobody knows! If you are a crypto project, you must decide what your principles are.
接下来会发生什么？没人知道！如果你正在开展一个加密项目，你必须决定你的原则是什么
I have been expressing the same consistent principles for the last seven years. [Applause]
我过去七年一直表达同样的观点 同样的原则。 [掌声]
The reason is really simple: it takes too much bloody homework to [shift between different ones],
原因很简单：[在不同的准备功课之间转换]需要做太多的准备功课
and remember how to be consistent with what I said before, if I'm not following what I actually believe in.
记住，如何遵循自己的信仰， 如何把持言行一致
Some people in our industry noticed that recently. Inconsistencies can happen very quickly.
我们行业的一些人最近注意到了这一点。 不一致可能很快发生
Some crypto projects recently faced that kind of fork in the road.
最近有些加密项目面临着这样的岔路口
They decided to focus on different principles and tried to change the trajectory of projects we care about.
他们决定专注于不同的原则, 并试图改变我们关心的项目的轨迹
Lately, one of them is all about cheap payments, at the expense of decentralisation and privacy.
最近，其中之一是关于廉价支付， 以牺牲分布式和隐私为代价
Apparently, to the people [involved in it], privacy is only useful for illegals and money launderers...
显然，对于[参与其中]的人，隐私仅对非法移民和洗钱者有用......
who are [engaging in] wash trading and bucket shops.
他们从事洗牌交易和投机商号
Ooh, scary! [Laughter] If that is the road you want to go down, the light you see is not the end of the tunnel...
哦，吓人！ [笑声]如果那是你想要的道路， 当你走下去，你看到的光不是隧道尽头......
but an oncoming Facebook train that already has the principle-less, privacy-less market staked out.
但一列即将到来的Facebook火车已经具备了无原则，无隐私的市场特性
They already have two billion users, lots of money and technology people who will run right over you.
他们已经有20亿用户，有大量的资金和技术人员，他们会对你横加指责
If you haven't differentiated based on your principles -- or worse, you don't have any principles --
如果您没有根据您的原则进行区分 - 或者更糟糕的是，你没有任何原则 -
and decided with your recently hired MBA that you are really interested in shareholder return on investment,
你最近聘用的MBA，对股东投资回报感兴趣，你就根据这个来做决定
and the best way to do that means shedding a few of these "silly," "idealistic" principles,
而最好的方法就是扔掉其中一些“愚蠢”，“理想主义”的原则，
then guess what?
猜猜那将会怎么着？
Once you start shedding principles, now you're [competing against] Facebook.
一旦你开始抛弃原则， 你就会[与Facebook竞争]
What is Facebook, if not the world's most [powerful] principle shedding machine? [Laughter]
什么是Facebook，难道它不是世界上最[强大]的无原则机器吗？ [笑声]
It started with few [principles to begin with], and has since developed a mechanism for shedding them...
它一开始没有什么原则，并且后来发展了一种机制来摆脱原则......
faster than you can imagine, with billions of dollars in marketing tickling your dopamine receptors.
速度比你想象的要快，数十亿美元的市场营销刺激你分泌多巴胺
"Don't worry! The future is candy colored and bright... as long as we are still profitable."
“别担心！......只要我们还能盈利，那么未来就是糖果色的，光明的“
They can shed principles faster than you, with more money, better user interfaces,
他们可以比你更快地摆脱原则， 用更多的钱，更好的用户界面，
and a bigger user base than you.
来获取比你更大的用户群
So if your game is shedding principles to make profit, that is a game you will not win.
所以，如果你因为盈利压力而减少原则 ，这是一场你不会赢的游戏
Facebook will win that game. They will win it over PayPal and JPMorgan Chase.
Facebook将赢得那场比赛。 他们战胜PayPal和JPMorgan Chase
They will sure as hell gonna win it over a little ragtag crypto project that says, "We don't need privacy."
他们肯定会赢过一个不起眼的加密项目，上面写着：“我们不需要隐私。”
"We just want to be a fast payment network...
“我们只想成为快速支付网络......
that collaborates with law enforcement and [enables] surveillance [capitalism]."
与执法部门合作 ，并且[启用]监视[资本主义]。“
Figure out what your principles are.
弄清楚你的原则是什么
Everybody will need to stop, take a breath, and figure out how to differentiate. It is actually pretty easy.
每个人都需要停下来，深吸一口气，然后弄明白如何区分。这实际上非常简单
If you get into a fight with someone who doesn't hold principles, a corporation, that is not immoral,
如果你和一个没有原则的人、一个公司发生争执，这不是不道德的，
because that requires having negative morality.
因为他们有的是消极的道德
[They are] amoral, which means no moral guidance whatsoever. The absence of any moral compass.
[他们]是不道德的，这意味着没有任何道德指导。没有任何道德指南针
Morality doesn't even enter their ROI equation. Morality is not on the spreadsheet.
道德甚至没有进入他们的ROI方程 道德不在电子表格中
If you are going to pick a fight with them, differentiate on the thing they can't compete with:
如果你打算和他们一起战斗， 在他们无法竞争的事物上与众不同
align yourself with the one project that is truly open, borderless, neutral, censorship resistant, transparent,
让自己与一个真正开放的项目保持一致， 无国界，中立，抗审查制度，透明，
auditable, private, and immutable.
可审计的，私有的和不可变的
There are a few of those, I think. Privacy currencies will get quite a run [for their money].
我想，其中有一些隐私货币[跟他们的货币比起来]将会有相当大的吸引力
There is a [growing need] to really focus on privacy, because Facebook won't.
人们将会越来越关注隐私，但Facebook不会
Things just got really interesting. As a technologist, I am so excited.
事情真的很有趣。 作为一名技术专家，我很兴奋
I have been jumping up and down all day. I can't wait to see how this plays out.
我已经兴奋一整天了， 我迫不及待地想看看它是如何发挥作用的
That has been my lifelong fascination: watching technological systems interact with society...
这一直是我的兴趣所在：看着技术系统与社会互动......
and change the world.
并改变世界
As these developments roll out, I will see if I can pick up a few clues as to where these things are going.
随着这些进展的推进，我将看到我是否可以找到一些线索，了解这些事情的走向
To have that vision has been my life's goal. As a technologist, I have been jumping up and down.
拥有这个愿景一直是我人生的目标。 作为一名技术专家，我一直在上下跳跃
As a human being, I am horrified that we are opening the door to a future that is truly terrifying and dystopian.
作为一个普通人，我感到恐惧的是 我们正在打开一扇通真正可怕和反乌托邦的未来之门
We are giving power to some of the most ruthless, unaccountable corporations out there.
我们正在把权力交给一些最无情的人和不负责任的公司
Not to fight against governments, but in many cases to join them hand-in-hand.
我们不是为了对抗政府 但在许多情况下，他们携手并进
They will ensure that while we're exploited by ruthless politicians on one side,
他们将确保当我们被剥削的时候， 一边是无情的政客
we are also exploited by ruthless business people on the other, in an alliance between corporation and state.
另一方面，在公司与国家之间的联盟中，我们也被无情的商人利用
That is called fascism, only this isn't your grandpa's fascism.
那被称为法西斯主义， 只是这不是你爷爷所经历的法西斯主义
This is a whole neo-feudal environment that we have never seen before.
这是一个我们以前从未见过的，完整的新封建环境
A lot of people will make the mistake [of assuming] that if it doesn't come in a leather uniform designed...
很多人会错误的认为 如果它不是充斥着皮革制服设计......
by Hugo Boss, with clashing colors, caricature parades, and screaming into megaphones, it is not fascism.
带着Hugo Boss，缤纷的色彩，漫画游行， 对着扩音器尖叫，这不是法西斯主义
But fascism today can come in a slick user interface with beautiful colors, accessible 24/7, through your browser...
但今天的法西斯主义可以通过一个灵活的用户界面来实现，通过美丽的颜色，支持浏览器24/7全天候访问...
and the most convenient location whether your phone is on or off.
以及最方便的定位功能， 无论您的手机是打开还是关闭
It is part of your life. It allows you to share photos with Grandpa, the same one who fought Nazis.
这是你生活的一部分。它允许您分享与爷爷的照片，就是与纳粹战斗的你的爷爷
It is the ultimate irony.
这是最大的讽刺
We need to be very careful about what we do next. This is deadly serious stuff.
我们需要非常小心我们接下来做什么。 这是致命的严重事情
Society is not ready for this because we've never been here before.
社会还没有做好准备 因为我们以前从未到过这里
While I am fascinated to watch, at the same time, I am deeply troubled.
虽然我着迷于观看， 但与此同时，我深受困扰
I am not afraid because I think Bitcoin can't compete. I am afraid because I believe a lot of people don't care.
我并不害怕，因为我认为比特币不会终结。 但我很害怕，因为我相信很多人都不在乎
A lot of people will go for the easy, convenient, mindless, repetitive, seductive, hypnotizing rhythm...
很多人都会轻松，方便，无意识，重复，诱人，催眠的节奏......
of a Facebook feed, through which they will lose their freedom and their future. Thank you. [Applause]
通过Facebook 的催眠， 他们将失去他们的自由和未来。谢谢。 [掌声]